Okay, בוקר טוב, Boker Tov, today's דף daf is קי"ח Kuf Yud
Chet 118. We pick up three lines from the bottom. We're dealing
with a משנה Mishna that talks about saving שלוש סעודות shalosh seudot
worth of food, which has led to the
גמרא Gemara to a discussion about food on שבת. Shabbat. So, most
recently we discussed the idea of having שתי הלחם, shetei halechem,
and now we continue three lines from the bottom. כיצד נפלה דליקה.
Keitzad nafla deleika. So, what is the specific idea of three meals?
So it says, well, if there's a fire on שבת, Shabbat, so
it depends when the fire occurs. Does it occur on Friday night?
Does it occur שבת Shabbat day? You can basically save the number
of meals that are left to be eaten. And then you have
the position of רבי יוסי Rabbi Yosi that says you can always
save שלוש סעודות. shalosh seudot. So let's look at what the גמרא
Gemara says. תנו רבנן: Tanu rabanan: כמה סעודות חייב אדם לאכול בשבת?
kama seudot chayav adam le'echol beShabbat? How many meals are you obligated
to eat on שבת? Shabbat?
שלוש, Shalosh, three, which is pretty implicit in the משנה, Mishna, or
at least it's implicit that that was the practice. Now we're seeing
that you're חייב. chayav. רבי חידקא אומר ארבע. Rabbi Chidqa omer arba.
Now he has a fascinating position. רבי חידקא Rabbi Chidqa says four.
אמר רבי יוחנן: Amar Rabbi Yochanan: משום מקרא אחד דרשו. mishum mikra
echad darshu. They both have learned out from one פסוק. pasuk. ויאמר
משה אכלוהו היום. Vayomer Moshe ichluhu hayom. משה Moshe says, by the
מן, man, eat it
today. We're counting the number of היום. hayom.
כי שבת היום לה'. ki Shabbat hayom l'Hashem. That's two היום. hayom.
היום לא תמצאוהו בשדה. hayom lo timtza'uhu basadeh.
Today you won't find it in the meal in the field. רבי
חידקא סבר הני תלתא היום לבר מאורתא. Rabbi Chidqa savar hani tlata
hayom lebar me'orsa. These three היום hayom are daytime, other than the
nighttime meal. ורבנן סברי, Verabanan savri, the rabbis say, בהני דאורתא behani
de'orsa includes the night. So anyway, sometimes because it's היום, hayom, היום,
hayom, היום, hayom, by the מן, man, היום, hayom, היום, hayom, היום.
hayom. Anyway, that indicates how many different types of meals you're supposed
to eat. Not exactly clear why היום hayom means the number of
meals you're supposed to eat. Also not exactly clear the idea of
four. Three you can understand. I mean, for us maybe four makes
sense because we normally have three. I mean, we don't do four,
but I'm just saying the idea of doing something extra for שבת,
Shabbat, an extra meal for שבת, Shabbat, you know, you understand like
it's a meal special, you know, עונג שבת, oneg Shabbat, specially designated,
makes the day different. Where רבי חידקא Rabbi Chidqa gets to, where
רבי חידקא Rabbi Chidqa gets to four, it could be like I
just said, because although the גמרא Gemara basically indicates that there were
two major meals like a midday meal and an evening meal, it
also does indicate that there was like basically the idea of having
something to eat in the morning. So maybe again, for him, the
four is to you know, he sort of sees it as the
standard is three. Although that's not so clear, I mean, the גמרא
Gemara does make it seem like it basically understands the idea as
שתי סעודות shte seudot a day that comes out in many, many
different contexts, that it understands that you have generally two meals a
day. I would say maybe it's a similar idea to the שתי
הלחם, shetei halechem, the doubling of you know, the bread that fell
on ערב שבת. erev Shabbat. So although that happened on Friday and
it was supposed to be divided between Friday and שבת, Shabbat, but
the same way we have two loaves of bread, maybe for him
we have double the number of meals. Anyway, the גמרא Gemara learns
it out from the היום. hayom. We, of course, know that we
eat שלוש סעודות shalosh seudot for שבת. Shabbat. So now the גמרא
Gemara is going to try to see if we can, now this
is a debate of תנאים, Tannaim, so we're going to look at
other תנאי Tannaic material and see whether which pretty much all assumes
the rabbinic position of three, the rabbis' position of three, but the
גמרא Gemara is going to see if it might fit with רבי
חידקא. Rabbi Chidqa. So let's take a look. תנן. Tnan. We've taught
in our משנה. Mishna. נפלה דליקה בלילי שבת. Nafla deleika beleilei Shabbat.
If the fire broke out on Friday night, מצילים מזון ג' סעודות,
matsilin mazon gimmel seudot,
you can save the food for three meals. מאי לאו, Mai lav,
isn't it talking? Because the assumption here is once the meal is
over, you can no longer save food for that meal. So מאי
לאו דלא אכל. mai lav delo achal. Doesn't it mean it broke
out Friday night before you had your שבת Shabbat meal? So and
you see that you only have three meals for שבת. Shabbat. לא
דאכל. Lo de'achal. No,
it means after you had your meal Friday night, then the fire
broke out. So it would work with רבי חידקא Rabbi Chidqa because
you had one meal and then there are three left. All right,
let's keep on going. It's just going to be the same thing.
שחרית, Shacharit, if the fire broke out שבת Shabbat morning, מצילים מזון
שתי סעודות, matsilin mazon shtei seudot, you save two meals worth of
food. מאי לאו דלא אכל, Mai lav delo achal, doesn't it mean
it broke out שבת Shabbat morning before you had your meal? So
you see there's only two meals left on שבת Shabbat day after
the night. לא דאכיל. Lo de'achil. No, it meant you had your
שבת Shabbat meal and there's still two meals left. So it's like
רבי חידקא. Rabbi Chidqa. It could work with the idea of four.
במנחה, Bemincha, so the משנה Mishna continues, if it broke out at
מנחה mincha time, מצילים מזון סעודה אחת, matsilin mazon seuda achat,
you save food for one meal. מאי לאו דלא אכל, Mai lav
delo achal, doesn't it mean you haven't yet had your מנחה mincha
meal, your third סעודה seuda and you see that you have a
total of three? לא דאכל. Lo de'achal. No, it means you had
your מנחה mincha meal. You had three and there's still one left
to go for רבי חידקא. Rabbi Chidqa. So the משנה Mishna can
work according to רבי חידקא. Rabbi Chidqa. So that was all a
very big stretch and now the גמרא Gemara says one minute. דהא
מדקתני סיפא, Daha midektane seifa, the end of the משנה Mishna says,
רבי יוסי אומר לעולם מצילים מזון ג' סעודות. Rabbi Yosi omer leolam
matsilin mazon gimmel seudot. At any time the fire breaks out, you
always get to save the max, which is three סעודות. seudot. מכלל
דתנא קמא ג' סבירא ליה. Michlal detanna kamma gimmel sevira leh. You
see that the תנא קמא Tanna Kamma also holds that there are
three סעודות seudot on שבת. Shabbat. It's a whole debate of the
תנא קמא Tanna Kamma and רבי יוסי Rabbi Yosi is do you
deduct the meals you've already eaten? Can you save the max, three
all the time, or you only save based on the number of
meals you have left? But in principle, everybody agrees that there are
three סעודות seudot on שבת. Shabbat. Three meals on שבת. shabbat. אלא
מחוורתא משנתינו לא כרב חסדא. ela makhvarta matnitin lo k'rav khisda. Very
good. It makes the best sense that the משנה mishna is not
like רב חסדא, Rav Khisda, which is clear. The simple sense to
the משנה mishna is three סעודות seudot on שבת. shabbat. Okay, והא
דתנן, v'ha ditnan, that which we taught in the משנה, mishna, והא
דתנן, v'ha ditnan, מי שיש לו מזון שתי סעודות, mi she'yesh lo
mazon shtei seudot, this is going to be a very nice little
not so much a digression, but pulling in evidence of how many
meals people eat from discussions in פאה peah and elsewhere about what
your responsibility is to poor people in terms of feeding them and
giving them food for the day and for the week, how much
food do we assume they need? Let's take a look. It says:
מי
שיש לו, mi she'yesh lo, this is a famous משנה mishna in
פאה peah that talks about, it's actually quite interesting, you know, פאה
peah is, we normally assume
that look, what is our obligation of
צדקה? tzedaka? If you look narrowly defined, the obligation of צדקה tzedaka
is if an עני ani comes and asks you for money you're
supposed to give that. How about sort of to proactively provide funds
for the poor? So nowadays we talk about an obligation of
מעשר כספים. ma'aser kesafim. But מעשר כספים, ma'aser kesafim, which
is like a new articulation, a new expression to the מעשר ma'aser
of grain that exists in the תורה torah at a time when
A, we don't live in ארץ ישראל, eretz yisrael, well a lot
of us don't live in ארץ ישראל, eretz yisrael, and B, that
our economy is not based on agriculture but on commerce, so it's
a very nice way of giving a new
form to that idea, but it's certainly not, but it's not like
the biblical מצוה. mitzvah. So that raises of course the question to
okay, so if I'm not raising grain and I only have to
give צדקה tzedaka when an עני ani comes to me, do I,
can I ignore the poor the rest of the time? And anyway,
even if I am doing grain,
מעשר ma'aser that went to the עניים aniyim was only two out
of every six seven years, שמיטה shmita was okay a full years
with it. But anyway, so it's interesting that the discussion in the
משניות mishnayot for a more proactive and I would even say communal
responsibility towards the עניים aniyim comes at the end of the משניות
mishnayot in פאה, peah, because פאה peah is, that is the real
way on a year-to-year basis the poor were supported. Again, assuming an
agricultural society, that every time there was the harvest, the droppings, you
read רות rut and that's the image you get, right? That all
the poor are waiting during the harvest and they're going to gather
up the stuff that's dropped, the לקט, leket, and the stuff that's
forgotten, the שכחה, shikhcha, and the corners of the field, the פאה,
peah, and that was take place, although every
individual farm owner left it on his own, nevertheless it was taking
place all at the same time and it was to some degree
a communal and a nationwide type of experience. So that was really
the regular way in which the poor were provided for on an
annual basis without having to come and ask, and also it took
place to some degree at a communal level. So it's at the
end of the משניות mishnayot of פאה peah where the משנה mishna
discusses this idea of the קופה kuppa and the תמחוי, tamchui, of
this communal soup kitchen and this communal gathering of funds to distribute
to the poor because that actually was where the rabbis sort of
gave, as opposed to this later idea that occurred more at the
Middle Ages at the time of the ראשונים rishonim of מעשר כספים,
ma'aser kesafim, which is very much individualized, this is more where the
rabbis gave expression to like פאה, peah, לקט, שכחה, Leket Shichcha not
just in terms of agriculture and at the communal level. So that's
here we're quoting these משניות mishnayot at the end of פאה peah
about those, the soup kitchen and the communal fundraising that is done
for the poor, yes.
פאה לקט ושכחה peah leket v'shikhcha are what converts are supposed to
be taught.
Right, so that's interesting. That is one of the, of all the
things mentioned for what you teach converts, that is one of them
and raises interesting questions why that is singled out. But certainly one
of the things that it emphasizes is the communal, the communal and
the moral obligations that are included in a life of מצוות mitzvot
and not just the ritual ones. Okay so now the גמרא, gemara,
now the גמרא gemara says, והא דתנן, v'ha ditnan, that which we
taught in the משנה, mishna, מי שיש לו מזון שתי סעודות לא
יטול מן התמחוי. mi she'yesh lo mazon shtei seudot lo yitol min
hatamchui. Now the soup kitchen, the תמחוי tamchui is basically the soup
kitchen, the soup bowl. What they would do is they would go
around household to household, people would knock on the door and whatever
you were cooking or something you would put like a ladle worth
into this big soup
bowl. Stone soup. Whatever, yeah, well hopefully everybody was cooking פליישיגס, fleishigs,
or whatever, I don't know maybe they'd have a פליישיג fleishig kind
and מילכיג milchig kind. But anyway, they'd go around and everybody would
contribute a little bit of what they're cooking and then they would,
the poor would line up or they'd go whatever, they'd make it
available to the poor and everybody would come and take some food
for the day. So that was like a daily soup kitchen. That
was the תמחוי. tamchui. So it says if you have food for
two days, for two meals, so basically you're covered for today, it's
assumed each day we eat two meals. So today you're covered, you
have enough bread on you, whatever, to last you for two meals,
לא יטול מן התמחוי, lo yitol min hatamchui, you cannot take from
the soup kitchen. The soup kitchen is only for people that don't
have, don't have enough to eat even for one day. Okay, maybe
a one meal but you don't have two meals, you don't have
enough to eat for the whole day, then you're entitled to take
from the soup kitchen. Now, מזון ארבע עשרה, mazon arba'asar, ארבע, arba,
if you have fourteen meals, which is a week's worth of
food, לא יטול. lo yitol. And this would be a different collection
that you would go around and people would have to pay, give
a certain amount of money, it would be assessed based on, there
would be the whole discussion about who assesses how much people have
to pay, who determines how to distribute the funds, but anyway based
on different people's degree
of wealth and financial ability, people would contribute different funds to this
charity box, and then people could come and get money for the
week to spend for a week's worth of food. רש"י Rashi says
you obviously you can't do both. I mean if you're going to
the soup kitchen, how can you be taking funds for the week?
So רש"י Rashi says this is for people that maybe רש"י Rashi
says it's like maybe people that started life
from a better financial position, now they're poor, and it's real embarrassment
to be taking, lining up for a daily soup kitchen. But presumably
anybody would be entitled if you don't want to go to the
soup kitchen, you can take the funds for the week and then
spend it on your distribute use it out over the week, it
would be 14 meals worth for the whole week. Okay, but you're
not allowed to take those funds if you have 14 meals worth
of food or the money for that. You can only take those
funds if you don't have enough money to provide for you for
the week, then you're entitled to take these funds for the meals
for the week. Yes.
Money's only for food, what about clothes?
Right, so that's a good question, right, that's a good question, we'll
see a little bit of that coming up, this was specific funds
that were raised for food. I mean again it's somewhat parallel to
the לקט leket, שכחה shikhcha, and פאה, Pe'ah, which doesn't mean that
they didn't have other ways of assuming that responsibility in the other
areas, but it seems like the primary, first the most basic substance
was food. Right, essentially, right, exactly.
It's an interesting question that if I go and I take the
money for the food, can I choose to spend less of it
on food and use some of it for shoes? Right, right, it's
an interesting question, I have to check that, I don't know that
offhand. All right, so it says like this, if you have enough
for 14 meals, you're not allowed to take from the charity box.
So okay, so anyway, the point for us is just that we
say 14 meals. Well, in a week is שבת, Shabbos, or that's
15 meals. So מני? mani? לא רבנן ולא רבי חידקא, lo Rabbanan
velo Rabbi Hidka,
not the Rabbis who say three meals on שבת, Shabbos, not רבי
חידקא Rabbi Hidka that says four. אי רבנן חמש סרי הווי, ei
Rabbanan chamish sarei havyei, according to the Rabbis it should be 15.
אי רבי חידקא שית סרי הווי, ei Rabbi Hidka shis sarei havyei,
according to רבי חידקא Rabbi Hidka it should be 16. לעולם רבנן,
le'olam Rabbanan, really it's the
Rabbis. דאמרינן ליה damrinan leh and we say to him,
מאי דבעית למיכל באפוקי שבתא, mai de-ba'it lemeichal be-afukei shabsa, look,
what you were going to eat on מוצאי שבת, Motzei Shabbos, look,
we gave you 14 meals, okay, that includes שבת Shabbos and it
includes Sunday, so
every day is the meal of the night and the middle of
the day, so the food that you were going to eat Sunday,
for that you were going to eat Saturday night for your Sunday
food allowance, rather than waiting till מוצאי שבת, Motzei Shabbos, eat it
for שלש סעודות, Shalosh Seudos, which works good if it's a late
שבת Shabbos because anyway, right, in the summer you eat your שלש
סעודות Shalosh Seudos at 6, 7 o'clock, who needs dinner after that?
So that's what we say, you do it out of 14 because
rather than the Saturday night meal, you'll have it late שבת Shabbos
in your שלש סעודות. Shalosh Seudos. So גמרא Gemara says אכליה בשבתא,
achlei be-shabsa, so לימא רבנן ולא רבי
חידקא. leima Rabbanan velo Rabbi Hidka. Fine, so that works according to
the Rabbis, but it doesn't work according to רבי חידקא Rabbi Hidka
that says you have to have
four meals on שבת, Shabbos, excuse me, which would get you 16.
אפילו תימא רבי חידקא, afilu teima Rabbi Hidka, even you can work
according to רבי חידקא. Rabbi Hidka. דאמרינן ליה, damrinan leh, here's how
we get the fourth meal, מאי דבעית למיכל במעלי שבתא, mai de-ba'it
lemeichal be-me'alei shabsa, so your Friday afternoon meal, אכליה לאורתא, achlei le-ortasa,
eat for Friday night. Okay, so therefore yes, you can have you
can pay for Friday, שבת, Shabbos, and Sunday, but by moving the
Friday afternoon meal into שבת Shabbos and the Saturday night meal into
שבת Shabbos you can get your four meals on שבת. Shabbos. So
גמרא Gemara says what are you talking about? וכולי יומא דמעלי שבתא
בתעניתא מותבינן ליה? vekulei yoma de-me'alei shabsa be-ta'anisa mosivin leh? We make
him fast the entire ערב שבת Erev Shabbos so that he can
use that one meal for Friday night?
You know what you're supposed
to do actually according to the רמב"ם?
Rambam? Not fast, not רמב"ם, Rambam, but you're not supposed
to have like a big meal, not fast. אלא, ella, so rather,
הא מני רבי עקיבא היא, ha mani Rabbi Akiva hi, so this
is רבי עקיבא. Rabbi Akiva. You're right, it doesn't matter רבנן Rabbanan
or רבי חידקא, Rabbi Hidka, I can still explain to you the
14. How can I explain to you the 14, what about רבנן
Rabbanan and רבי חידקא Rabbi Hidka who should get up to 15
or 16? Because it's רבי עקיבא. Rabbi Akiva. What does רבי עקיבא
Rabbi Akiva say? דאמר de-amar רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva says,
עשה שבתך חול ואל תצטרך לבריות, asei shabboscha chol ve-al titztarech le-briyos,
rather you should make your שבת Shabbos like a weekday, don't do
anything special for שבת Shabbos rather than having to become dependent on
other people. So rather than having to get to a level where
you need to take charity from other people, rather to not do
anything special for שבת Shabbos than to need to take charity in
order to do something special. Now the problem, right, the problem with
it is... You're already taking charity. So you're already נצרך לבריות. nitztrach
labriyos. You're already dependent on other people and it's actually interesting, like
one of the first משנה ברורהs Mishnah Berurah in
on הלכות שבת Hilchos Shabbos discusses this. That on the one hand
we say,
there's a מדרש Midrash that says like לוו עלי ואני פורע, luvu
alay va'ani poreia, borrow money from me for שבת Shabbos and I
will pay you back, so you're supposed to spend extra money to
make it nice for שבת Shabbos even if it means borrowing money
and so on. Another גמרות Gemoras that talk about about
maybe even taking צדקה tzedakah for שבת Shabbos and here גמרא Gemara
that says עשה שבתך חול ואל תצטרך לבריות. asei Shabboscha chol ve'al
tztarech labriyos. לבריות, labriyos, לבריות, labriyos, לבריות. labriyos.
So anyway, so he reconciles all of this rather than say there's
different opinions by saying that borrow and I'll pay you back is
somebody that actually, if I remember correctly, I didn't double check it
but I think the משנה ברורה Mishnah Berurah right at the beginning
of הלכות שבת, Hilchos Shabbos, I think he says that that means
somebody who's not poor you need to borrow money for that, you
had a cash flow issue but it's not like you're really taking
charity. And in terms of charity do you take or not? He
says look, if you already are on the are taking communal funds
in general, to take a little extra money to make שבת Shabbos
nicer, that's fine. This statement of רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva which is
better your שבת Shabbos should feel like a weekday and don't take
money is somebody who has yet to be in a position where
they need to take charity, where they need to take communal funds.
So that's a very nice resolution and you can understand that also
psychologically and communally, you don't want to make a person start to
have to take צדקה tzedakah just because they need to make שבת
Shabbos nice. If you're already taking צדקה tzedakah why not take a
little extra? But that's not the way the גמרא Gemara applies it.
The גמרא Gemara applies it here the guy that's taking money for
14 meals and we say don't take for 15. So what does
it mean? I'm already putting myself in this position. So רש"י Rashi
says it's not about you the עני ani that don't make yourself
dependent. It's actually about you that about us the givers, you're not
entitled to demand from us that we should get extra money just
so you could have a nice
שבת. Shabbos. We'll give you in order to give you your basic
two meals a day, but it's not fair to demand from us
extra money just for your מצוה mitzvah of עונג שבת. oneg Shabbos.
Now that is
interesting because the first משנה Mishnah in ערבי פסחים Arvei Pesachim it
says אפילו afilu what? Yeah, אפילו עני המתפרנס מן הצדקה
afilu ani
hamisparnes
min hatzedakah like לא יפחתו לו
מארבע כוסות, lo yifchesu lo me'arba kosos,
right that even an עני ani exactly the scenario that's getting his
food from the soup kitchen we have to provide him for ארבע
כוסות. arba kosos. Okay, now that might be דוקא davka that's once
one day a year and that's exactly because at least one day
he should feel like a free person, a wealthy person, now the
other 364 days he feels like an עבד eved more or less.
So okay, so that's one day a year, but for שבת, Shabbos,
on a weekly basis, it's not our responsibility to provide for him
עונג שבת. oneg Shabbos. That's at least the way רש"י Rashi reads
it, not so much about him becoming dependent on other people which
he already is. Okay, so that's that issue about why we say
14 meals. והא דתנן veha detnan and how about the other thing
we talk in in משנה פאה? Mishnah Peah? אין פוסקין לעני העובר
ממקום למקום מככר בפונדיון מארבע סאין בסלע.
ein poskin le'ani
ha'over mimakom lemakom mikikar befundyon me'arba sa'in besela. Now if you have
a person this is also what type of עניים aniyim are entitled
for your town's צדקה. tzedakah. So if it's a guy that's just
passing through and how much and he's not even sleeping over the
night, you have to give him bread for two meals. How much
is that? So it's an עני העובר ממקום למקום, ani ha'over mimakom
lemakom, he's just passing through. You buy him a loaf of bread,
a ככר בפונדיון kikar befundyon with a פונדיון. pundyon.
A פונדיון pundyon is a it's a 12th of a סלע. sela.
So you give him a bread that costs a פונדיון pundyon when
4 סאה se'ah goes to a סלע. sela. So that means if
you do the math, if and this פונדיון pundyon is a 12th
of a סלע, sela, so that the פונדיון pundyon gets you is
a 1/48th of a סאה se'ah of grain. Okay so did I
do that right? Hold on, I might have done it wrong. Yeah
but I might have given you the wrong numbers. Hold on, let
me double check רש"י. Rashi. No no no, I think a פונדיון
pundyon is a 48th, excuse me.
Yeah that's what it says in,
okay I got you the numbers. A פונדיון pundyon is a 48th
of a סלע, sela, right is a 48th of a סלע. sela.
Now a סלע sela will get
you 4 סאה. se'ah. Will get you 4 סאה. se'ah. So a
פונדיון pundyon will get you a 12th of a סאה. se'ah. Okay
so anyway, if a 12th of a סאה se'ah of grain made
into a loaf of bread, okay that's what you buy him. So
you buy him a loaf of bread made with a 12th of
a סאה se'ah grain, basically it's a loaf of bread that will
provide for two meals worth. Two meals worth of bread. That's what
you give this עני ani that is passing through the town. Okay
now נותנין לו nosnin lo if he sleeps over the night in
the town, נותנין לו פרנסת לינה, nosnin lo parnasas linah, you give
him what he needs for sleeping over. We'll see what this means
but this is less about food and more about the other provisions
that רבקה Rivka was referring to. ואם שבת ve'im Shabbos if he
spends שבת Shabbos in the town, נותנין לו מזון ג' סעודות, nosnin
lo mazon gimmel seudos, you give him three meals. Okay, so here
you see that actually you give somebody for three meals worth. So
exactly how that works before when we said we only give 14
meals for the whole week, anyway we won't worry about that, but
here at least says for שבת Shabbos *Shabbos* you give him three
meals. So לימא רבנן היא כדרבי *leima rabbanan hi k'derabbi*, again it
sounds like the rabbis not רבי Rebbi, חזקיה *Rabbi Chizkia* that there's
three meals on שבת Shabbos *Shabbos*. לעולם רבי Rebbi חזקיה *L'olam Rabbi
Chizkia*, could really be רבי חזקיה *Rabbi Chizkia*, כגון דאיכא סעודה seuda,
בהדיה *kegon d'ika se'uda bahadei*, he comes into the town with one
meal. So we give him three, makes four. Why we're assuming that,
I don't know. But the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says דאמרינן ליה הא
דאיכא בהדך *damrinan leh ha deika bahadach*, the meal you came in
with אכליה *achlei*, you eat on שבת Shabbos *Shabbat* and you've got
four, we only need to give you three. So now the גמרא
Gemara *Gemara* says וכי אזיל בריקא אזיל *vechi azil bereika azil*. So
that doesn't work because presumably if he's leaving מוצאי שבת Shabbos. *Motzaei
Shabbat*, he's only here for שבת Shabbos, *Shabbat*. What are we going
to do, send him away with no food? Right, it's sort of
like the whole story about like the עגלה ערופה *Eglah Arufah*, right,
ידינו לא שפכו *yadeinu lo shafchu*, we didn't, we weren't מלוה *melaveh*
him, you know,
we didn't shirk on our responsibility to accompany him, to provide for
him. You don't send a guy away with no food, with no
צידה לדרך *tzedah laderech*. So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*, well, maybe he
won't get there by the next—he's leaving at night. So the גמרא
Gemara *Gemara* says דמלוינן ליה סעודה seudah בהדיה *demalvinan leh se'uda bahadei*,
no, when he leaves, we'll give him another meal. Okay, I know.
So it's reading a lot into this משנה *Mishna*. He came with
one, we'll give him one. Anyway, again, the simple sense of all
of this material is
שלוש סעודות seudos, *shalosh se'udot*. רבי חזקיה *Rabbi Chizkia*
is a very strange position. Anyway, the
גמרא Gemara *Gemara* just ends this. מאי פרנסת לינה *Mai parnasat lina*?
What does it mean, provisions for the night? אמר רב פפא Amar
Rav Papa. *Amar Rav Papa*, פוריא *purya* a bed, ובי סדיא *uvei
sadya* and a blanket, or רש״י *Rashi* says is also a
type of—something to
use under his head for a pillow. So here you go, right,
at least for the עני *ani* that is passing through, you do
provide for him for not for more than just food. Okay, so
that was a very interesting and nice digression getting us a little
touching on some really important issues about צדקה tzedakah *tzedakah* and communal
responsibility and also this whole question about borrowing money for שבת Shabbos,
*Shabbat*, becoming dependent, responsibilities to provide, and so on. Now we continue
a little with the food issue and then we will turn to
a major focus on more אגדתות *Aggadatas* associated with this whole topic.
So let's take a look. תנו רבנן *Tanu rabbanan*. קערות שאכל בהן
ערב שבת Shabbos *Kearot she'achal bahen erev Shabbat*, מדיחין לאכול בהן שחרית
*madichin leechol bahen shachris*, you can wash them in order to eat
on them שבת Shabbat, *Shabbos* morning, שחרית *shachris*. The ones you used
שבת Shabbat, *Shabbos* morning, מדיחין לאכול בהן בצהריים *madichin leechol bahen betzaharayim*,
you can wash them to eat in the afternoon, בצהריים *betzaharayim*. In
the afternoon, מדיחין לאכול בהן במנחה *madichin leechol bahen bemincha*, you can
wash them to eat
מנחה *mincha* time if you're going to have
another סעודה *se'uda* or what—or any other food. מן המנחה ואילך *Min
ha-mincha va'ilech*, things that you ate on from מנחה *mincha* time onward,
שוב אינו מדיח *shuv eino madiach*, you don't wash them anymore.
It's מוצאי שבת Shabbat
*Motzaei Shabbos* and you want to move it away? Yes. אבל כוסות
וקיתוניות וצלוחיות *Aval cosot vekitonyot vetzluchiyot*,
but cups, glasses, and pitchers and—and you know other types of
things used for liquids, for drinks, bottles, מדיח והולך כל היום כולו
*madiach veholech kol hayom kuloh*, you can wash the entire day, לפי
שאין קבע לשתייה *lefi she'ein keva leshtiya* because there is no fixed
amount of drinking. There are certain times you have meals, but you
can drink at any time during the day and therefore it's always
legitimate to wash it. As Michael says, we touched on this the
other time, right? Why can you not wash at the end of
the day for at least the plates? So רש״י *Rashi* says אין
הכנה אלא לחול *ein hachana ela lechol*, you're doing it for the
weekday. And as I told you, some people are very מקפיד makpid
*makpid*, they leave all the food over after שלוש סעודות seudos, *shalosh
se'udot*, the plates start, I don't know, attracting bugs or whatnot. And
the real הלכה halacha? *halakha* is that this is not a categorical
statement. This is only if the reason you're doing it is for
the sake of the next meal. But if you're doing it so
that the room doesn't look disgusting on שבת Shabbat. *Shabbat*, you know,
you don't like having a table with all that stuff, you can
certainly clean up the table, move the plates to the sink. If
you don't like walking into the kitchen with all these dirty dishes
in the sink, you can also do the dishes, okay, as long
as you're doing it because of the current desire not to have
these things around, that's okay. But if you're doing it so that
it's ready for after שבת Shabbat, *Shabbat*, that is a problem. Okay,
now the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* continues
with moving on to אגדתא *Aggadata* related to שלוש סעודות *shalosh se'udot*
and related topics and this will be for the rest of today
and going through till tomorrow. Yeah, exactly.
Michael will be subbing for me tomorrow. Okay. אמר רבי שמעון בן
פזי אמר רבי יהושע בן לוי משום בר קפרא *Amar Rabbi Shimon
ben Pazi amar Rabbi Yehoshua ben Levi mishum Bar Kappara*. כל המקיים
שלוש סעודות בשבת ניצל משלוש פורעניות *Kol hamkayem shalosh se'udot baShabbat nitztal
mishalosh puraniyot*, is saved from
three bad events or three afflictions. מחבלו של משיח Mashiach, *Mechevlo shel
mashiach*, the birth pangs of משיח *Mashiach*, מדינה של גיהנום Midina shel
Gehennom, *midina shel Gehennom* from the judgment of גיהנום Gehennom *Gehennom*, וממלחמת
גוג ומגוג Gog u'Magog, *umimilchemet Gog u-Magog* and from the war of
Armageddon. So those are pretty big things to be saved from. Yeah.
מחבלו של משיח *Mechevlo shel mashiach*, right, מחבלי משיח *mechevlei mashiach*, מחבלי...
יצלו וירווחו *Yitzalu yirvacha*. Okay? So if you do עונג שבת Oneg
Shabbos. *oneg Shabbos* and you have three סעודות *se'udot*, you are saved
from the חבלי משיח Chevelei Mashiach, *chevlei mashiach*. כתיב הכא יום ksiv
hacha yom, *Kesiv hacha yom*, it says here יום yom *yom*. We
learned that three סעודות *se'udot* from the three times it says יום
*yom*. וכתיב התם Ukhtiv hatam: הנה אנכי שולח לכם את אליה הנביא
*Ukesiv hasam hinei anochi sholeiach lachem et Eliya hanavi*. לפני בוא יום
ה׳ Yom Hashem. before the יום of ה׳ Hashem comes, so basically
the way the מהר״ל Maharal explains all of this or the, I
forget, maybe the מהרש״א, Marsha, I think the מהרש״א, Marsha, anyway is
that, you know, is that this is about עונג שבת. Oneg Shabbos,
שבת Shabbat, is מעין עולם הבא. me'ein olam haba. All of these
things are sort of a מעין עולם הבא, me'ein olam haba, משיח,
גוג ומגוג, Gog u'Magog גיהנום Gehennom, is one form of עולם הבא,
olam haba, not the good one. Anyway, anyway, so if you make
שבת Shabbat, all about עונג, oneg, all about joy and all about
מעין עולם הבא me'ein olam haba and you express this through your
three סעודות, you get straight to that sort of pleasure or, you
know,
the the tranquility of עולם הבא olam haba without having to go
through the pain that precedes it which is like the חבלי משיח,
גוג Gog ומגוג and so on. Okay, so that's יום ה׳. מדינה
של גיהנום, Gehennom. the judgment of גיהנום, כתיב הכא יום, ksiv hacha
yom, כתיב התם יום עברה היום ההוא, ksiv hasam yom evra hayom
hahu, that day is a day of anger, the day then God
will judge people in גיהנום. מלחמת גוג ומגוג, Milchemas Gog u'Magog, כתיב
הכא Ktiv hacha: יום, it says here day, כתיב התם ביום בוא
גוג, ksiv hasam beyom bo Gog, the day that גוג comes. Okay,
so yeah, what?
I mean, I don't know if you want to touch on this
now.
Probably not. Go ahead, yeah.
Well I'll ask it anyway, you know, because I mean these days
a lot of us don't eat three סעודות, so can we discuss
like you know, how do we?
Okay, yeah, well I'll talk about it, I'll address it now, I'll
maybe address it whatever next time I do the דף, daf, but
that is a question about this idea about you know already the
פוסקים poskim discuss that some people want מקפיד makpid on on שלש
סעודות, shalsudos, some answers are well maybe תורה Torah counts instead of
שלש סעודות, shalsudos, every time we do the דף היומי, Daf Yomi,
that can count.
I don't know, anyway, so we okay, I'll address that, not today,
but I will address it. אמר רבי יוחנן משום רבי יוסי, Amar
Rabbi Yochanan mishum Rabbi Yosi, כל המענג את השבת, kol hime'aneg es
HaShabbos, anybody now we're more abstracting it, not just about שלש סעודות,
shalsudos, but anybody that gives pleasure you know makes שבת Shabbat, into
a day of pleasure, gives pleasure you know
on שבת. Shabbat This is as opposed to before you might remember
we discussed the emphasis was more about כבוד, kovod, about doing things
to show honor to שבת, Shabbat. and that
emphasis had a lot to do with how we dress. Right here
we're about on the עונג שבת, oneg Shabbat about having pleasure, which
a lot focuses on the types of food we eat, having an
extra סעודה, having food, you know having nice food and so on.
So let's take a look. כל המענג את השבת, Kol hime'aneg es
HaShabbos, anybody that gives pleasure gives pleasure to שבת, Shabbat, נותנין לו
נחלה בלי מצרים, nosnin lo nachala bli meitzarim, you give them, is
given a bequest, an inheritance without any
limit, שנאמר אז תתענג על ה׳. she'ne'emar az tisanag al Hashem. Then
the פסוק posuk says וקראת לשבת עונג לקדוש ה׳ מכובד, vekrasa la'Shabbos
oneg likodosh Hashem mechubad, you call שבת Shabbat a day of pleasure,
the holy the holy day of God honorable, אז תתענג על ה׳,
az tisanag al Hashem, then will you experience pleasure with God, והרכבתיך
על במתי ארץ, vihirkavticha al bamsai aretz, I will make you ride
onto the high places of the land,
והאכלתיך נחלת יעקב אביך, ve'he'achalticha nachalas Yaakov avicha, the inheritance of יעקב
Yaakov your father. So how's that a נחלה בלי מצרים, nachala bli
meitzarim, an inheritance without limits? לא כאברהם שכתוב בו, Lo ke'Avraham she'kosuv
bo, not like אברהם, Avraham, where it says קום התהלך בארץ, kum
hithalech ba'aretz, go rise up, walk in the land לארכה ולרחבה, le'orkah
u'lerachbah, so to it's with in the plains, but still בארץ, ba'aretz,
this land, nothing more. ולא כיצחק שכתוב בו, Velo ke'Yitzchak she'kosuv bo,
כי לך ולזרעך אתן את כל הארצות האל, ki lecha u'lezaracha etein
es kol ha'aratzos ha'eil, to you I've given you these lands, but
still these, nothing more. אלא כיעקב, Ella ke'Yaakov, it's the נחלה nachala
of יעקב, Yaakov, שכתוב בו ופרצת, she'kosuv bo u'faratzta, you shall burst
forth, and to be פורץ poretz also means like to burst through
a gate, you know, burst forth any limit. You'll burst forth ימה
וקדמה צפונה ונגבה, yama va'keidma tzafona va'negba, in all directions, there's no
limit, so that will be a נחלה בלי מצרים. nachala bli meitzarim.
So I want to say two things about this. Number one, the
sort of most obvious point is that this idea of like of
pleasure, you know of enjoyment is, maybe it's not so obvious, anyway
I think this is a point the מהרש״א Marsha makes, you know,
first of all enjoyment, you could learn the word מצר meitzar not
only to be a boundary, you know, a limit, but from the
word צר, tzar, like affliction. So pleasure is the opposite of affliction.
But also the sense of pleasure is that sense of feeling like,
you know, like not constrained. So that sense of being not constrained
and just enjoying and relaxing, that's this idea of נחלה בלי מצרים,
nachala bli meitzarim, an inheritance without constraints. But I did do want
to say something about this יעקב. Yaakov.
I have spoken about this מדרש midrash before and tied it to
another מדרש midrash that compares אברהם, Avraham, יצחק, Yitzchak, and יעקב Yaakov
where it says, you know, יעקב Yaakov wakes up and he says
אין זה כי אם בית אלהים וזה שער השמים, ein zeh ki
im beis Elokim vizeh shaar hashamayim, right, when he wakes up on
הר הבית, Har HaBayis, בית אלהים. beis Elokim. So the גמרא Gemara
focus on a פסוק posuk that says לעתיד לבוא le'asid lavo the
גוים goyim will say, you know, let us get up and we'll
go up לבית אלהי יעקב, le'veis Elokei Yaakov, to the house of
the God of יעקב. Yaakov. Why בית אלהי יעקב? beis Elokei Yaakov?
Not בית אלהי אברהם beis Elokei Avraham or יצחק? Yitzchak? So it
says לא כאברהם, lo ke'Avraham, very similar structure to the
מדרש. midrash. לא כאברהם שקראו הר, Lo ke'Avraham she'krao har, right, בהר
ה׳ יראה, behar Hashem yeira'eh, לא כיצחק שקראו שדה, lo ke'Yitzchak she'krao
sadeh, ויצא יצחק לשוח בשדה לפנות ערב, vayeitzei Yitzchak lasuach basadeh lifnos
erev, אלא כיעקב שקראו בית, ella ke'Yaakov she'krao bayis, you know, אין
זה כי אם בית אלהים. ein zeh ki im beis Elokim. So
it's very interesting, right, that The Avraham and Yitzchak, that their experience
of God was in wide open, without boundaries, on a mountain, in
a field. So there it's the נחלה nachala has limits. יעקב, Yaakov,
the experience of God was בית אלוהים, Beit Elohim, a house which
is with walls and limits, that's the נחלה בלי מצרים. nachala bli
metzarim. Right, it's an interesting sort of like contrast, parallel and contrast.
So my read anyway was, was that, you know, if you try
to experience sort of, you know, that the idea of of
of well I'll just give you one version of it in terms
of what it's in terms of like
one way I applied this was like in terms of the issue
of like, you know, raising children or providing structure. So you give
somebody, you know, a home which has limits and structures and boundaries
but also what it has in it is intimacy and warmth and
that sense
of, you know, of just well of intimacy. Anyway, so you the
providing of that sense of structure and boundaries and the home ultimately
gives somebody the confidence to go out and to go without any
limits, right, but that starts with creating a type of a structure
that then allows them to burst forth. So that's anyway one application
I've done, you know, I've used it in other ways as well,
but it's interesting to sort of put those two side by side
and to see the almost reversal with the exact same type of
a structure. Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara continues.
רב נחמן בר יצחק אמר: Rav Nachman bar Yitzchak amar: ניצול משעבוד
גלויות. nitzol mishibud galiyot. If you appropriately have pleasure on שבת, Shabbat
same similar idea, you're saved from these things which are about afflictions.
You're saved from the being subjugated in exile. כתיב הכא: והרכבתיך על
במותי ארץ, vehirkavtikha al bamotei aretz, I'll make you ride I'll
I'll ride you on the high places of the land. וכתיב התם:
ואתה על במותימו תדרוך, ve'atah al bamoteimo tidrokh, you will you will
stomp on their high places, so about you having having dominion and
not the other nations having dominion over you. אמר רב יהודה אמר
רב: Amar Rav Yehuda amar Rav: כל המענג את השבת, kol ham'aneg
et haShabbat, נותנין לו משאלות לבו. notnin lo mish'alot libo. Anybody that
has pleasure on שבת, Shabbat you give all the desires of their
heart. So again this sense of like of expansiveness, I think is
the word I was looking for, right, no limits, you're just enjoy
it, this expansiveness, you give them all the desires of their heart.
שנאמר: Shene'emar: והתענג על השם, vehit'aneg al Hashem, ויתן לך משאלות לבך,
veyiten lekha mish'alot libekha, he'll give you all the desires of your
heart. עונג זה איני יודע מהו? Oneg zeh ani yodei'a mahu? What
is this pleasure, when are you supposed to be having pleasure? Why
that's an emphasized. אלא כשהוא אומר: Ella k'shehu omer: וקראת לשבת עונג,
vekarata laShabbat oneg, you call שבת Shabbat a pleasure, הוי אומר זה
שבת, hevei omer zeh Shabbat, that is the עונג oneg
of שבת. Shabbat, במה מענגו? Bemah me'ang'o? Now practically, how
do you experience עונג שבת oneg Shabbat. beyond having an extra סעודה
which we mentioned before? So רב יהודה בריה דרב שמואל בר שילת
משמיה דרב אמר: Rav Yehuda brei d'Rav Shmuel bar Shilat mishmei d'Rav
amar: בתבשיל של תרד, betavshil shel tared, you have a special cooked
beets, that's a special עונג שבת. oneg Shabbat. Okay, so רש"י Rashi
says, yes this was חשוב, chashuv, says רש"י. Rashi. Okay, ודגים גדולים,
vedagim gedolim, and big fish, וראשי שומים, veroshei shumim, and heads of
what do you call it, of garlic. So רש"י Rashi says: חשובים
היו להם. chashuvim hayu lahem. Okay here he adds the word להם.
lahem.
Okay, so anyway, so these are these were their examples meaning but
also presumably meaning you don't have to go crazy overboard, you don't
have to have a שמיר, schmear, you know you have like a
special very nice little special dish, you know, that's that's עונג שבת.
oneg Shabbat. And רב
חייא בר אשי אמר רב,
Rav Chiya
bar Ashi amar Rav, and maybe this just takes it one step
further but I think it's in the same thrust: אפילו דבר מועט,
afilu davar muat, even if it's a very small thing, אם לכבוד
שבת עשו, im lichvod Shabbat aso, if you're doing it special for
שבת, Shabbat הרי זה עונג. harei zeh oneg. That's an עונג. oneg.
Now it's interesting because you could have said הרי זה כבוד, harei
zeh kavod, right, you did something special for שבת, Shabbat, that shows
you're showing it honor, but the point is also even if it's
a little עונג oneg is you know because the pleasure is the
fact that you made the effort? The fact that you made the
effort is the כבוד, kavod, the עונג oneg is the actual pleasure,
but even then, even a little עונג oneg for שבת, Shabbat that's
עונג. oneg. Yes, Charlie.
I have two things. It doesn't mention meat.
Well that might have been a good point because that might have
been even assumed
maybe or it might have been or it might have been very
expensive and not something that you could assume. I think the whole
point here is to speak about small even small things count for
עונג שבת.
oneg Shabbos Second,
so they're talking about the the wonderful things are gonna happen to
people who observe שבת, Shabbat. such as not being enslaved anymore. This
is at a time when שבת Shabbat, observance among Jews was universal
and yet we were in גלות. galut. Right.
So yeah
I mean how would you say how do you say how do
you say these things if you know make these promises when they
don't exactly come true? Alright, you know it's Midrashic and it's sort
of it's sermonics so I don't know what to tell you. I
don't think I don't think people were expecting going up to the
rabbi and saying: You know I had עונג שבת Oneg Shabbat last
year last week and I didn't get my my desires of. my
heart. I don't think people took it that literally.
Okay, anyway, another way to interpret it would be you aren't going
to feel oppressed the way you would be if you weren't observing
שבת.
Shabbos Oh, that could be, right? Everything is relative.
Can we say even a little thing or is the הלכה? halacha
Yeah.
Yeah. Yeah. אמר רב פפא. Amar Rav Papa: Yeah. Okay. So now
the גמרא Gemara, says, "הרי זה עונג." Harei zeh oneg. מאי
היא? Mai hi? What would be an example of a little thing?
אמר רב פפא: Amar Rav Pappa, כסא דהרסנא, Kasa de-harsena, like a
type of fish fried in batter. Okay. אמר רבי חייא בר אבא
אמר רבי יוחנן, Amar Rabbi Chiya bar Abba Amar Rabbi Yochanan, כל
המשמר שבת כהלכתו, Kol ha-meshamer Shabbat ke-hilchato, now moving from עונג שבת
Oneg Shabbat to keeping שבת, Shabbos anybody that observes שבת Shabbos according
to its real laws, all the details, אפילו עובד עבודה זרה כדור
אנוש, afilu oved avodah zarah ke-dor Enosh, even if a person worshiped
idols like the period of אנוש, Enosh, which is when they started
"אז הוחל לקרא בשם ה׳" az huchal likro be-shem Hashem when עבודה
זרה avodah zarah started, מוחלין לו, mochelon lo, it's forgiven. שנאמר, She-ne'emar,
"אשרי אנוש יעשה זאת." Ashrei enosh ya'aseh zot. Praise to אנוש Enosh
who does this, right? יעשה זאת שומר שבת מחללו. Ya'aseh zot, shomer
Shabbat me-chalelo. אל תקרי מחללו, Al tikri me-chalelo, keep שבת Shabbos from
desecrating it, אלא מחול לו, ella machul lo, everything else will be
forgiven to him. Okay, so yeah, pretty extreme. So you know, so
the I forget one of the מפורשים meforshim say, so why it's
like you get, I think the מהר״ל, Maharal, why you get so
much reward is because this whole idea that שבת Shabbos is the
unique gift to בני ישראל Bnei Yisrael and it uniquely connects them
to God, so that's why it has all of this extreme reward
because it really shows, it really shows, thank you, it really shows
your belief in God and that that's ultimately you know what you're
totally committed to. So that you know so, how about the fact
you're עובד עבודה זרה? oved avodah zarah? Alright, that's just יצר הרע.
yetzer hara. Okay.
It is true, by the way, that עובד עבודה זרה oved avodah
zarah did not always mean as we translate as like a rejection
of God and Judaism, you know, in a very sort of pagan
society or whatever there could be other reasons why you're sort of
playing along and doing those types of things. I know, but you're
not say you're כופר, kofer, right? Keeping שבת is like you're מקיים
כולו mekayem kulo and even עבודה זרה avodah zarah is מחול לו.
machul lo. All right, which is a pretty extreme statement. All right.
אמר רב יהודה אמר רב: Amar Rav Yehuda Amar Rav: אלמלא שמרו
ישראל שבת ראשונה, Ilmalei shamru Yisrael Shabbat rishonah, had the Jewish people
kept the first שבת, which we read about last week's פרשה, parshah,
לא שלטה בהן אומה ולשון, lo shalta ben ummah ve-lashon, they never
would have been ruled over by any nation or language. שנאמר, She-ne'emar,
"ויהי ביום השביעי יצאו מן העם ללקוט," Vayehi bayom hashevi'i yatze'u min
ha'am lilkot, they went out to gather, so they violated, right? Even
if they weren't like did a מלאכה, melachah, but they still went
against it, they were supposed to not go out and they went
out to gather. וכתיב בתריה, U-ktiv batreh, and at the end of
that פרשה, parshah, last week's פרשה, parshah, it says "ויבא עמלק," Vayavo
Amalek, that was because they had made themselves vulnerable now by violating,
now they were able to be attacked by עמלק. Amalek. Of course,
a little problem that "ויבא עמלק" Vayavo Amalek is not immediately juxtaposed,
there are a few other events that occur between them, which maybe
also would have been deserving of "ויבא עמלק," Vayavo Amalek, but anyway,
this is the דרשה drashah that שבת in a way, like it's
the flip side of it's like, you know, it's everything is מחול
לו, machul lo, it connects you totally to God, that if you
because of the violation of שבת, it exposed us, it made us
vulnerable, and particularly that first one might have like been very much
about sealing our identity. אמר רבי יוחנן משום רבי שמעון בן יוחי,
Amar Rabbi Yochanan mishum Rabbi Shimon ben Yochai, and this is a
famous דרשה: drashah: "אלמלא משמרים ישראל שתי שבתות כהלכתן," Ilmalei meshamrin Yisrael
shtei Shabbatot ke-hilchatan,
if we would only keep two שבתות Shabbatot correctly, because you know
you need at least a little momentum to show it's not just
a, you know, like an anomaly. Anyway, "מיד נגאלין," miyad nig'alin, we
would be redeemed immediately. So that's the flip side of we never
would have been, you know, subjugated, here we can actually reverse it
if we would just keep two שבתות. Shabbatot.
שנאמר, She-ne'emar, "כה אמר ה׳ לסריסים אשר ישמרו את
שבתותי,"
Koh amar Hashem lasarisim asher yishmoru
et
shabbatotai, those who keep my שבתות Shabbatot plural. וכתיב בתריה, U-ktiv batreh,
"והביאותים אל הר קדשי ושמחתים בבית תפלתי." Ve-haviotim el har kodshi ve-simachtim
be-veit tefilati.
Okay,
so just keeping two שבתות, Shabbatot, again, all this with this sense
that the observance of שבת shows our complete sort of connection to
God and therefore would have protected us and would bring the גאולה.
Geulah. אמר רב יוסף, Amar Rav Yosef, now, now
we're going to get into a like a different type of a
sort of genre here after talking about עונג שבת and keeping שבת.
We're talking about praising people, praising you know specific acts that people
do. "יהא חלקי מאוכלי שלש סעודות בשבת," Yehei chelki me-ochlei shalosh se'udot
be-Shabbat,
from those who eat שלש סעודות shalosh se'udot on שבת, meaning, which
implies that it wasn't done so much. Also, if you need a
lot of this rhetoric, you also part of the reason presumably is
because it wasn't always done universally. So anyway, he says, "If only
I would get the merit of those who are always מקפיד on
שלש סעודות." shalosh se'udot. And now we're going to get to a
whole list of "יהא חלקי עם," Yehei chelki im, my portion should
be with those that do X, that this is a thing about
like particular things that are either in themselves very important, or some
of the מפורשים meforshim just say, even if these things are not
necessarily more important than other things, but there's an idea here about
maybe trying to take one מצוה mitzvah and really specialize in it,
like take one מצוה mitzvah and that's your special מצוה, mitzvah, and
that's actually a very beautiful idea. You know, I don't think, which
is, I don't think common enough in our community, the idea of
not yeah we you know we try to do הלכה as best
as possible, but like there's one... one thing you really are מקפיד
*makpid* on and do it in the most beautiful way and put
a lot of emphasis on it. It gives you a very deep
and profound connection to the whole system if you find one thing
that you really like is very, very special. So that's going to
be sort of the genre here of יהי חלקי yehai chelki. עם
*Yehei Helki Im*. Yes.
I heard something similar for people who are never going to be
a big תלמיד חכם *Talmid Chacham* for everything to at least do
one area really well.
Right. Right. So that I think that that is a very nice
idea and one way of seeing what's the point of what's being
said here. Okay. So now we continue. A lot of these are
רבי יוסי Rebbi Yose *Rabbi Yosi*. אמר רבי יוסי Amar Rabbi Yosi.
*Amar Rabbi Yosi*, so רבי יוסי Rabbi Yosi *Rabbi Yosi* said, יהי
חלקי yehai chelki. מגומרי הלל בכל יום *Yehei Helki migomrei hallel bechol
yom*, my portion should be with those that complete the הלל *Hallel*
every day. איני *Eini*? Is that true? והאמר מר הקורא הלל בכל
יום הרי זה מחרף ומגדף *Veha'amar Mar hakorei hallel bechol yom harei
zeh mecharev umegadef*. If somebody says הלל *Hallel* on a daily basis,
it's like they are cursing and blaspheming. I'll discuss that in a
minute. No, כי קמנינן בפסוקי דזמרא *ki kamniyan bipsukei dezimra*. No, he's
not talking about the הלל *Hallel* like what we call the הלל
המצרי *Hallel Hamitzri* that we say on the, you know, that we
say on the חגים *chaggim*. He's talking about saying פסוקי דזמרא *Psukei
Dezimra*. Now, why are right why is הרי זה מחרף ומגדף *harei
zeh mecharev umegadef*? So רש״י *Rashi* says because if you're saying הלל
*Hallel* every day, the, you know, how we say whatever, you're making
it like just a song, you're not really making it like it's
a true expression of, you know, of religious fervor, of religious meaning.
You could also say, and this is an interesting question about, you
know,
that on the one hand, the רמב״ן *Ramban* says the purpose of
ניסי מצרים *Nisei Mitzrayim* were to make us sensitive to the fact
that everything is a נס *nes* and even the natural order is
a נס *nes* and it's all from God. On the other hand,
if you basically equate everything, so every day you're talking about like,
you know, ניסי מצרים *Nisei Mitzrayim* and so on, so nothing is
special. So if like everything is a נס *nes*, then you don't
see God in those special moments, right? If you try to and
that also sort of a little bit that maybe no, but a
little bit that goes back to the other דרשה *drasha* I was
telling you before about God being in the mountain, God being in
the field, or God being in the house. God is everywhere, but
if you basically if God is everywhere, then to some degree God
is nowhere. If you have a concentrated place where you experience God,
right, in the house, then you're more sensitive to seeing God elsewhere
as well rather than say, oh, everything is amazing. So it's also
I think part of the idea of saying הלל בכל יום *Hallel
bechol yom*, oh, everything, it's always amazing, I'm always living with ניסי
השם *Nisei Hashem*. To some degree, maybe desensitizes you rather than heightens
the sensitivity. That's one way of understanding it. Anyway, so פסוקי דזמרא
*Psukei Dezimra* is also interesting because that's not as extreme, that's actually
what פסוקי דזמרא *Psukei Dezimra* if you think about it, a lot
of the פסוקי דזמרא *Psukei Dezimra*, הללויה *Halleluyah*, you know, is is
about nature praising God. It's not about the supernatural, the ניסי מצרים
*Nisei Mitzrayim*, which is the הלל *Hallel* we say on יום טוב
*Yom Tov*, it's about nature praising God, which is the appropriate way
of experiencing God during the rest of the week. This is the
גמרא Gemara *Gemara* that mentions פסוקי דזמרא *Psukei Dezimra*. You know, this
whole institution of saying פסוקי דזמרא *Psukei Dezimra*, ברוך שאמר *Baruch She'amar*,
ישתבח *Yishtabach*, whatever, it's not in the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*. Okay, this
גמרא Gemara *Gemara* mentions פסוקי דזמרא *Psukei Dezimra*. What's included in פסוקי
דזמרא *Psukei Dezimra*? You look at רש״י *Rashi*. רש״י *Rashi* says, פסוקי
דזמרא *Psukei Dezimra*, it's about eight lines down in the narrow lines,
שני מזמורים של הילולים הללו את השם מן השמים הללו אל בקדשו
*shenei mizmorim shel hillulim hallelu et Hashem min hashamayim hallelu El bekodsho*.
So according to רש״י *Rashi*, you got a pretty short פסוקי דזמרא
*Psukei Dezimra*. You say two of the הללו׳ס *Hallelus* and you're done.
Okay, two of the פרקים *prakim* of the פסוקי דזמרא *Psukei Dezimra*.
So this is but anyway, this is the idea and it's clear
that it wasn't being done widespread or by everyone, and saying some
type of פסוקים *psukim* that are not the הלל *Hallel* of נס
*nes*, but the הלל *Hallel* of God in nature.
So based on that, give a different interpretation. So the reason why
you're מחרף ומגדף *mecharev umegadef* is because you only concentrate on ניסי
מצרים *Nisei Mitzrayim*, you're forgetting to to see God in nature. If
you see God in nature, then at least
oh, that's an interesting flip side. Meaning you're oh, you're basically saying
that you only see God in the miraculous things. That's a nice
point. Okay, that's a nice way of saying it too. Okay. אמר
רבי יוסי Amar Rabbi Yosi, *Amar Rabbi Yosi*. Now, moving more another
statement of רבי יוסי Rabbi Yosi, *Rabbi Yosi* back to the גמרא
*Gemara* five lines down, יהי חלקי מהמתפללים עם דמדומי חמה *Yehei Helki
mi'hamitpalelim im dimdumei chamah*. My portion should be with those that pray
with like the reddening of the sun, with the with like the
rays of the sun, with like basically it's like ותיקין *Vatikin*, like
exactly at sunrise. אמר רבי חייא בר אבא אמר רבי יוחנן מצוה
mitzvah להתפלל עם דמדומי חמה *Amar Rabbi Chiya bar Abba amar Rabbi
Yochanan mitzvah le'hitpalel im dimdumei chamah*. It's a מצוה *mitzvah* to do
this. אמר רבי זירא מאי קרא *Amar Rabbi Zeira mai kra*? Where
do you see it from the פסוק *pasuk*? יראוך עם שמש ולפני
ירח דור דורים *Yira'ucha im shemesh velifnei yareiach dor dorim*. They will
see you with the sun
and before the moon, you know, from generation to generation. So with
the sun means like with the rising of the sun. רש״י *Rashi*
actually also mentions it's not just sunrise and ותיקין *Vatikin*, it's also
before the moon comes out, he also means sunset and דאוונינג *davening*
at sunset. And those are maybe also ways in which you experience
God more during those moments of the day when you're feeling the
sun come up on the on the land, the sun going down.
It's more evokes more of this religious experience. So in addition to
a halachic point. ואמר רבי יוסי Ve-amar Rebbi Yose, *Ve'amar Rabbi Yosi*,
and רבי יוסי Rabbi Yosi *Rabbi Yosi* said, יהי חלקי מתי בחולי
מעיים *Yehei Helki mimetai becholi me'ayim*. My portion should be now we're
not talking about focusing on a מצוה *mitzvah*, but from those that
die with a sickness of the you know of like the intestines,
of the you know of the of the digestive tract. דאמר מר
*De'amar Mar* because we say... רובן של צדיקים tzaddikim מיתי בחולי מעיים.
The majority of צדיקים tzaddikim, die that way. What's so special about
dying that way? תוספות Tosafot says it's a very painful death and
therefore it atones for your sins, which is interesting. Others say that
basically what it does is it cleans your body out of all
of the waste products so that you basically go into עולם הבא
Olam Ha-ba with the least amount of גשמיות gashmius or certainly of
waste product. It's not exactly clear. תוספות's Tosafot interpretation is probably the
most פשט pshat that this sense about that even though nobody's looking
for suffering, maybe actually this idea that at the death some type
of כפרה kaparah associated with that. ואמר רבי יוסי, Ve-amar Rebbi Yose,
רבי יוסי Rabbi Yosi said, יהי חלקי ממיתי בדרך מצוה. Yehi chalki
mi-meisei be-derech mitzvah. My portion should be with those that die in
the performance of a מצוה because that's a real זכות, zechus, then
it's like you're connected to God at that last moment of your
life. ואמר רבי יוסי, Ve-amar Rebbi Yose, so those two about how
you die you can't control. Back to doing מצוות. mitzvos. יהי חלקי
ממכניסי שבת בטבריא ומוציאי שבת בציפורי. Yehi chalki mi-machnisei Shabbos bi-Tveriya u-motzi'ei
Shabbos be-Tzippori. I should be with those that bring שבת in in
טבריא Tveriya and that see שבת out in ציפורי. Tzippori. Because in
טבריא, Tveriya, טבריא Tveriya they were in a valley so they perceived
it to be sunset before the sun actually set below the horizon
because it went behind the mountains. So they brought in
שבת early. And in whatever ציפורי Tzippori they were on a mountain
so the sun appeared to still be above the horizon even when
it was below the horizon but because of the curvature of the
earth they still saw the sun. So they actually let שבת out
even later. Of course, שבת doesn't come out as soon as the
sun sets, it comes out as soon as the sky gets dark
and so on, but okay, the sky got darker later there. So
anyway, it's quite interesting. So it seems like and it also seems
like other people really cut it to the last minute and here
we're speaking about this emphasis about giving yourself תוספת שבת tosefes Shabbos
a little bit of a buffer, yes.
Well this seems that you actually follow whatever the local sun is
rather than the astronomical when it doesn't...
No, because if that were true then there wouldn't be anything special
about that. The point is that they do what they can do
based on what they see.
That's what I mean.
But that actually is earlier or later than is necessary. Right. Because
if that was what was necessary for them, there wouldn't be anything
special about being with them. What's special about being with them is
that they do it based on their measurements, but their measurements are
imprecise, but let's get it imprecise at least in the better direction
rather than in the worse direction.
Can they go back and forth
from one city to another? I don't know how close they are,
whether they're in the תחום. techum. Okay. ואמר רבי יוסי, Ve-amar Rebbi
Yose, יהי חלקי ממושיבי בית המדרש ולא ממעמידי בית המדרש. Yehi chalki
mi-moshivei beis ha-medrash ve-lo mi-ma'amidei beis ha-medrash. My portion should be, I
gotta tell this to my students, those that sit in the בית
המדרש, beis ha-medrash, make the בית המדרש beis ha-medrash sit, not those
that make it stand, which means רש"י Rashi says it means the
person assigned like are you the guy that goes around and says
'Alright everybody, time for בית מדרש, beis medrash, time for ישיבה, yeshiva,
everybody get out of breakfast, we're starting סדר' seder or that's מושיבי
בית המדרש. moshivei beis ha-medrash. מעמידי בית המדרש Ma'amidei beis ha-medrash is
the guy that gets up and goes like a clop and says
'It's lunch time.' Okay. I'd rather be the one that brings everybody
to בית מדרש beis medrash than the one that tells them to
go. It could also be not that you're in a position of
authority, it's just you're the one that's spending more time sitting, you're
more there early sitting down, you're not the first one to leave
when it's time to go. ואמר רבי יוסי, Ve-amar Rebbi Yose, although
this is הפעיל hif'il you cause others to sit or you cause
others to go. ואמר רבי יוסי, Ve-amar Rebbi Yose, יהי חלקי מגבאי
צדקה ולא ממחלקי צדקה. Yehi chalki mi-gabai tzedakah ve-lo mi-mchalkei tzedakah. My
portion should be amongst those that collect the צדקה tzedakah. and not
those that distribute it. Why not? You think distributing it you're actually
giving money to the, I mean everybody's part of the process.
But so רש"י Rashi has a very profound רש"י. Rashi. רש"י Rashi
says
ממחלקי, mi-mchalkei, I don't even know where to tell you the רש"י,
Rashi, it's between where it says ישעיהו נ"ו Yeshayahu nun-vov and שמות
ט"ז, Shmos tes-zayin, it's about I don't know two fifths of the
way down. Anyway says לעניים לצדקה, la-aniyim la-tzedakah, then we read in
בבא בתרא, Bava Batra, צדקה נגבית בשנים ומתחלקת בשלושה. tzedakah nitveis bi-shnayim
ve-mit-chaleket bi-shlosha. You need three people to distribute צדקה. והמחלקים אותה עליהם
לבדוק לפי הצורך Ve-hamchalkim osa aleihem livdok le-fi ha-tzorech and if you're
distributing it, you have to assess people's needs. וכל אחד ואחד, Ve-kol
echad ve-echad, every individual you have to assess their needs. ופעמים שקרובים
דעתם לרחם על זה U-pe'amim she-krovim da'atam leracheim al zeh
and sometimes they feel more compassion for one guy than the other.
ולחלק יותר מן הצורך Ve-lachlok yoser min ha-tzorech and they give him
more than they should be giving him. שאומדין אותו על פי ההלכה,
She-omdin oso al pi ha-halachah, they're more generous in their assessment of
what he needs. ואומדין את חבירו בצמצום, Ve-omdin es chavero bi-tzimtzum, the
other guy they're more stingy. So basically it's very hard to be
precise and to be impartial when you have to distribute the money
to the צדיקים, so to the עניים. aniyim. So this is something
that is really a tremendous challenge to do this well. ואמר רבי
יוסי, Va'amar Rabbi Yosei, יהי חלקי ממה שחושדין אותו ואין בו. Yehi
chalki mi-ma she-choshkin oso ve-ein bo.
My portion should be among those that are suspected of things and
they're and they don't have them that they're innocent of.
אמר רב פפא, לדידי חשדין ולא הוי בי. Le-didi chashkin ve-lo havi
bi.
I've been suspected about something that I did not do. Not exactly
clear what they're talking about. אני ידעי Ani Yedaya מהר"ל Maharal points
out what's the point? Why do you want to be? So it
says well look he says actually it's a very powerful piece in
the מהר"ל Maharal he says he says it's really... Actually, it's a
very powerful piece in the מהר״ל. Maharal. He says it's really a
terrible, terrible to be suspected. Everybody looks at you, everybody suspects you,
it's terrible. And so if you actually did something wrong and everybody
suspects you of doing what's something wrong that you actually did, fine,
you deserve the suspicion, and maybe that's a כפרה. kaparah. But if
you didn't do it and then you're getting it, I mean, that's
like a tremendous עונש onesh to be received, it's a tremendous
hardship, so to say that at least gives you tremendous reward because
if you're innocent and getting this, the same idea of like ייסורים
yissurin and when bad things happen they give you reward. But he
makes a nice parallel which is to the סוטה. Sotah. He says
what happened to סוטה? Sotah? She's suspected, and if she's innocent, what
does it say? ונקתה ונזרעה זרע. v'niktah v'nizra'ah zara. So she gets
this wonderful reward in response to being innocently suspected. So the sense
that it's a terrible thing to be suspected, he even adds like
pretty much everybody thinks that if you're suspected, where there's smoke there's
fire, they assume you've done it. So it's a terrible thing, and
if you're innocent, then you get this tremendous reward. Plus I still
would rather not be suspected, forget the and not get the reward.
אוי לי ואוי לקוני.
Oy li
v'oy l'koni. Exactly. So let's continue. אמר רבי יוסי. Amar Rabbi Yosi,
So רבי יוסי Rabbi Yosi... says, חמש בעילות בעלתי. chamesh be'ilot ba'alti.
Now since these statements of רבי יוסי, Rabbi Yosi. יהי חלקי יהי
חלקי יהי חלקי, yehai chelki yehai chelki yehai chelki,
here's another statement of רבי יוסי Rabbi Yosi not of the same
genre. I had sex five times with my wife.
חמש בעילות chamesh be'ilot stayed with his wife.
Okay, he didn't say with his wife, that's true, fine, I hope
so anyway. Okay. ונטעתי חמישה ארזים בישראל v'natati chamisha arazim b'Yisrael and
I planted five cedar trees in Israel, ומן אינון u'man inun who
are they? רבי ישמעאל בר רבי יוסי, Rabbi Yishmael bar Rabbi Yosi,
רבי אלעזר בר רבי יוסי, Rabbi Elazar bar Rabbi Yosi, רבי חלפתא
בר רבי יוסי, Rabbi Chalafta bar Rabbi Yosi, they're all בר רבי
יוסי bar Rabbi Yosi I would hope, okay, רבי אבטילס בר רבי
יוסי, Rabbi Avtilos bar Rabbi Yosi, רבי מנחם בר רבי יוסי. Rabbi
Menachem bar Rabbi Yosi. Okay, so the גמרא says one minute, והאיכא
ורדימס? v'ha'ika Vardimas? What about ורדימס, Vardimas, he was one of רבי
יוסי's Rabbi Yosi. sons? So the גמרא says, היינו ורדימס היינו מנחם.
hainu Vardimas hainu Menachem. Oh no no, that was just a nickname
for מנחם. Menachem. ואמאי קרו ליה ורדימס? v'amai karu lei Vardimas? Why
was he called ורדימס? Vardimas? שפניו דומים לורד. she'panav domim l'vered. His
face was ruddy like a rose. I'm guessing it was probably a
Greek word, I don't know, did they say anything there, Charlie, in
the ArtScroll? Oh wait, it
is Greek.
Greek, the strong-hearted.
Strong-hearted,
okay there you go. למימרא דרבי יוסי מצות עונה לא קיים? l'meimra
d'Rabbi Yosi mitzvat onah lo kiyem? So the גמרא says, what do
you mean only five times he was with his wife? What do
you mean only five times? What about his obligation of עונה onah
to have sex on a regular basis with his wife? So the
גמרא says, אלא אימא חמש בעילות בעלתי ושניתי. ela eima chamesh be'ilot
ba'alti v'shaniti. I so it was five times I had sex with
my wife twice on the same night because according to the גמרא
says that somebody who wants to have smart male sons should be
בועל ושונה. bo'el v'shoneh. So that's a rereading of what רבי יוסי...
Rabbi Yosi You're reading it wrong, it means rose.
ורדימס Vardimas does mean rose in Greek? Yes. Really? That's interesting, so
the same ורד vered in Hebrew is also a Greek for rose.
Oh okay. Sometimes
it wasn't so you know what can I tell you. אמר רבי
יוסי, Amar Rabbi Yosi, back to רבי יוסי.
Rabbi Yosi, That was not יהי חלקי.
That was not יהי חלקי. Now we're just רבי יוסי's. Rabbi Yosi
No no no because it's all רבי יוסי. Rabbi Yosei But רבי
יוסי
Rabbi Yosei was suspected of no, being suspected is very...
Well that's what I was wondering, was it about being suspected and
assuming that suspicion is associated specifically with sexual suspicion, suspicion about sex?
I was wondering about that juxtaposition. No, no, no, it's just a
juxtaposition, it's just a juxtaposition, but these are statements of right, but
these are statements of רבי יוסי, okay. So let's just do one
or two more.
אמר רבי יוסי, מימי לא קריתי לאשתי אשתי ולשורי שורי. miyamai lo
kariti l'ishti ishti v'leshori shori. I never called my wife my wife
and my ox my ox. אלא לאשתי ביתי, ela l'ishti beiti, I
called my wife my house, ולשורי שדי, u'leshori sadi, and my ox
my field. Because your wife is there to make the home and
the ox is there to plow the field, which is you know
very obviously disturbing because I mean he's trying to make a point
about, I don't know what point he's making. A good expression. Right,
and it's also about things as well and also about these as
being instrumental. So you know he's sort of doing this as a
boast that he's emphasizing the importance of these things, but obviously it
makes the wife into something, into just instrumental. Trying to be positive.
They are, the גמרא, right, that somehow he's trying to say look
I'm trying to point out why she's important, it's important because she
makes the home, but obviously it's a problem. Anyway, by the way,
in the Aramaic the whole idea of the imagery of house and
wife is pervasive in the גמרא and the whole Aramaic word for
wife is דביתיהו, d'veiteihu, the wife
of, right? או לעולם יאמר אדם בתוך ביתו, o l'olam yomar adam
b'toch beito, ביתו beito often means sometimes means general household but most
basically it means wife. בית יעקב Beit Yaakov means women.
Well that's
how the גמרא interprets בית יעקב, Beit Yaakov, right. So let's just
read one more. אמר רבי יוסי, מימי לא נסתכלתי במילה שלי. miyamai
lo nistakalti b'milah sheli. I never actually looked at my ברית מילה,
bris milah, you know at my
genitals and amרו ליה לרבי, amru lei l'Rebbi, they said to רבי,
מאי טעמא קרו לך רבנו הקדוש? mai ta'ama karu lach Rabbeinu HaKadosh?
Why do you have that phrase the Holy Rabbi? אמר להו, Amar
lehu, מימי לא נסתכלתי במילה שלי, miyamai lo nistakalti b'milah sheli,
same answer. So if that's true why wasn't רבי יוסי called רבנו
הקדוש? Rabbeinu HaKadosh? So the גמרא says no, בדרבי מילתא אחריתא הואי
ביה, b'Rebbi milta achrita havai bei, רבי
had even a higher מדרגה. madreigah. שלא הכניס ידו תחת אבנטו. shelo
hichnis yado tachat avneto. He never put his hand into his genital
region, not only did he not look at it. Okay, I guess
we'll do one last one. ואמר רבי יוסי מימי לא ראו קורות
ביתי אמרי חלוקי, Va'amar Rabbi Yosei miyamai lo ra'u korot beiti imrei
chaluki,
the beams of my house never saw the hems of my garment.
I never sort of lifted up the skirts of my cloak, you
know, I was always fully clothed.
So that sounds like he should be קדוש. kadosh. Alright.
ואמר רבי יוסי, Va'amar Rabbi Yosei, I'm just going to read one
or two more. I'm sorry, I just got to get through the
רבי יוסיs. ואמר רבי יוסי מימי לא עברתי על דברי חברי. Va'amar
Rabbi Yosei miyamai lo avarti al divrei chaveirai.
I never went against what my friends would say. יודע אני בעצמי
שאיני כהן. Yodeia ani be'atzmi she'eini kohen. I know I'm not a
כהן. kohen. If I know one thing about myself, it's that I'm
not a כהן. kohen. אם אומרים לי חברי, Im omrim li chaveirai,
if my friends were to tell me, עלה לדוכן, aleh laduchan, hey,
let's go up to the דוכן, duchan, time for ברכת כהנים, birkat
kohanim, אני עולה, ani oleh, even though I'm absolutely certain that they're
wrong, I would go up, even when I know I'm totally right.
So this discusses is it wrong to go up for the דוכן
duchan if you're ישראל? Yisrael? But maybe that's his point. Obviously it's
an exaggeration, but it means even when I know I'm 100 percent
correct, I don't make מחלוקת, machloket, I go along with what my
friends say. Okay, which is that is a מדה, midah, you know,
to know that you're right and to still go along.
ואמר רבי יוסי, and רבי יוסי says, and this ממש mamash is
the last one, מימי לא אמרתי דבר וחזרתי לאחורי. miyamai lo amarti
davar vechasarti leachorai. I never said something and then checked behind me
to see who was listening. That is a big one, right? You
say something, wait a minute, who's here? Right? So if you don't
have to check behind you to see who's listening because you're always
careful about what you are saying.
Alright, and we will end there for today.